All
right, we'll pick up on the משנה Mishna there. So this משנה
Mishna is on page צדיק עמוד ב' Tzadik amud
bet by the way, smack in the middle. If
you look, this is at least the beginning part is like basically
pretty much a continuation of yesterday, same idea as, you know, let's
say he did this and wrote it this way and that way.
Having pictures will be very helpful, so if you don't have an
Artscroll, you should get one or I'll just draw it on because
it would really be rather difficult to understand it without any illustrations.
So, and so the first part is something the גמרא Gemara is
just going to get through, so to speak, and then actually we'll
sort of shift in tone to get into a completely different topic
which I think you'll find very interesting. Okay, so שייר מקצת הגט
וכתבו בדף השני והעדים מלמטה כשר. Shi'er miktzat haget uchtavo bedaf hasheni
vehayedim milmata kasher. So the first case is we say דף, Daf,
we sort of mean like יריעה Yer'a like in the Torah sense,
like a column. So like let's say you wrote the גט Get
in two columns. Just one גט, Get, two columns. Not yesterday was
like, you know, two גיטין Gittin each on one column. It's the
same גט, Get, part on one column and the rest on the
other column, and then the עדים Edim sign on the bottom of
the second column. So that's fine, כשר. Kasher. They sign at the
end of the גט Get after it's been written in two columns.
חתמו העדים בראש הדף. Chitmu hayedim berosh hadaf. So let's say again
this two-column גט, Get, but they signed at the like on the
top of let's say the second column. או מן הצד O min
hatzad or on the side, you know, like in the margins.
Wait. Hmm? He missed the page.
No, they didn't miss a page, but they just signed on the
side of the page. They didn't sign like on the bottom, you
know, you have a contract,
you sign at the end of it.
Here they signed like, you know, at the side of the גט
Get in the margins.
That's it, yeah. Yeah, מן הצד Min hatzad on the margins, right?
So you know, so that's what they did. או מאחוריו בגט פשוט
פסול O me'achorav beget pashut pasul or so they sign like on
the back, you know, in a regular גט Get and not like
the גט מקושר Get mekushar like we had before, you know, where
you're supposed to sign on like those other parts. But like a
regular one, you know, so that's not good. So now here's where
it gets the cases, you know, where we need to illustrate them,
and I'll do it, but you know, those of you that have
the Artscroll just look in there. הקיף ראשו של זה בצד ראשו
של זה והעדים באמצע שניהם פסולין.
Hekif rosho shel ze
betzad rosho shel ze vehayedim ba'emtza sheneihem pesulin. So let's say you
did, let's see,
it's kind of hard to draw
it this way, but like גט Get one and
then you did like the heads together, גט Get two.
Right, sort of like this. So you sort of moved, you have
two... yeah, I'm drawing it here, like so you did you sort
of did this, right? Then you had, you know, עד, Ed, עדים.
Edim. So that's case number one. That would not be good, so
I'll just write it down because we're going to get back to
it.
הקיף ראשו של
זה בצד ראשו של זה.
Hekif rosho
shel
ze betzad rosho shel ze. I'm just going to write it here.
הקיף ראשו של זה בצד ראשו של זה. Hekif rosho shel ze
betzad rosho shel ze. So that's no good. Okay? Right, you get
it? Like you know, you sort of took two גיטין Gittin and
like you sort of made them the heads, so to speak, and
the עדים, Edim, you know, are there. So these, you know, this
is like the
ראש הדף, Rosh hadaf, right? And then here's also like a sort
of a ראש הדף. Rosh hadaf. So okay, so that's not good.
I'm sorry for those of you just listening and not having the
benefit of a... you really can't do it any other way than
draw it, I think. So you don't know what to do with
that. Okay, now סופו של זה בצד סופו של זה והעדים באמצע,
Sofo shel ze betzad sofo shel ze vehayedim ba'emtza, so that's that's
the next case. Let me just get the picture over here. את
שנקראים עמו כשר. Et shenikra'im imo kasher. The ruling is the ones
that can be read with it are כשר. Kasher. And I'll and
I'll draw that too. So let's say you had this normally, you
know, גט Get one and then you had עד Ed and then
you did the, you know, גט Get two. I don't know how
to draw a two upside down, but you know. So you get
this, like this is... I mean the עדים Edim they are seeing
the right way. Yeah, yeah, exactly. סופו של זה בצד סופו של
זה. Sofo shel ze betzad sofo shel ze. Okay, so then so
the ruling is את שנקראים עמו כשר, Et shenikra'im imo kasher, which
would really be גט... Get... I'm sorry, no, wrong one. Which would
really be גט get one, right? Because you have the גט, get,
this is normal, right? And then you have the עדים edim at
the end, just like you would in any other thing, and then
this thing, you know, this is not the right way, right? So,
so that, that should be the way it is. You know, so
this good and obviously this is not. So okay. Now let's say
you did ראשו של זה בצד סופו של זה, rosho shel zeh
b'tzad sofo shel zeh, ראשו של זה בצד סופו של זה. rosho
shel zeh b'tzad sofo shel zeh. Okay. So if you did this,
this is sort of normal, so if you have גט get one,
so this part is the same, עד, ed, then you have גט
get two, right? So this is, so basically you have like just
sort of, if you will, like one normal גט get and then
the other one appended to it on the bottom. I guess I
can say that. Then it's the same, it's the same ruling, it's
את שנקראים עמו בסוף כאשר. et shenikraim imo basof kaasher. So, well
you know, it's the same idea. So then this would be good
and this would be not, not good because, you know, again it
should be like in the second גט, get, it'd be the עדים
edim on the head of a column, which we said isn't, isn't
good. You have to have the עדים edim afterwards. The bottom one
would sign and that would be good too, right? Yeah, the bottom
one would sign but we're not talking about that yet. You just,
you just, you just want to set it, like I guess look
at it this way, like you know, if you just had one
set of עדים, edim, someone like showed you this document, both of
them says this is my document of divorce, right? Then which one
would you let be divorced? So you know, if you didn't know
in a בית דין Beis Din and you read the עדים edim
and you know other proof, you'd, you'd say, you know, just objectively,
this seems to be going to since it's on the bottom of
גט get one, right? Right. So let's, right, so that's case one,
two, three. It's written in the second גט get after the עדים
edim signed. I'm sorry, it has to be what? No, it's written
in the second גט get after the עדים edim signed. Right, exactly,
exactly. Yeah, that's, that's exactly the reason why we say all this.
So, so those are the rulings and again for people listening on
the, or who will listen, if anyone, you know, you have these
awkward pauses, but I just have to draw the thing. All right,
fine. Now if you, this will call a case we did yesterday.
But yesterday was, you know, the more complicated case when you have
like two columns and you have like different יווני Yevani witnesses, sign
or signing in יווני, Yevani, then, you know, then or, or alternating.
This is the simple case. It teaches you the ruling when it
is good that, let's say גט שכתבו עברי וחתמו יוונית או יוונית
וחתמו עברי, get sheketavo Ivri vechattamo Yevanit o Yevanit vechattamo Ivri, עד
אחד עברי ועד אחד יווני. ed echad Ivri ve-ed echad Yevanit. It's
only one גט. get. So, well you know, you wrote it in
Hebrew, meaning let's say right to left and then you sign, you
know, in English, let's say whatever it is, you know, left to
right. Or the other way around. Or just again, one גט get
but you know, one signature was going right to left, the other
signature was going left to right. So some guy signed his name
in Hebrew and another guy signed his name in English, it's all
fine since it's only going on the one גט get that's there.
So you know, that's a simple, that's a simple case. Remember yesterday
was, you know, was a more funky case. So that's all good.
So now, listen, now final ruling is, wait it's good even though
it doesn't say. It doesn't say what? It's only one גט get
and then you have one, you have two witnesses. It just you
know, in the משנה Mishnah right, it just describes it and then
is it moving on to the next case when it says? No,
it says עד אחד עברי ועד אחד יווני. ed echad Ivri ve-ed
echad Yevanit. No, then the next one is כתב סופר ועד כשר,
katav sofer ve-ed kasher, right? So I'm just, I just, yeah, that's
on, it's on all this. So כתב סופר ועד, katav sofer ve-ed,
you remember we had that a whole bunch of times. Like let's
say you had the, the, this, the גמרא Gemara will explain it,
so but as we did before, it means כתב סופר katav sofer
really means חתם סופר, chatam sofer, right? It doesn't mean you just
had one עד, ed, rather you had the סופר sofer himself signing
and you also had another עד. ed. So we said that that's
good according to the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who said that, you
know, a שליח shliach is not allowed to change anything,
right? Because if a שליח shliach was allowed to change things, then
you worry that about the סופר sofer being embarrassed, remember all that?
And the סופר sofer will sign and the בעל baal didn't ask
him to and you
really had two, you really wanted
two people to sign, these other two people, but you know, they
didn't, the second one said all right fine, let the סופר sofer
sign, but that's not good because you're not allowed to change what
the בעל baal said. But if it's, you know, but
if
a שליח shliach is not allowed
to, you know, if you
hear it
from
a בעל baal directly, right, then
if you have a
סופר sofer signing then of course, they heard it
from
the husband because that's the way it goes. So anyway, that's the,
that's the way the גמרא's Gemara going to explain it, but just
reminding you. So that's okay. So now, now we're going to deal
with different ways of signing your name.
איש פלוני עד כשר.
ish ploni
ed kasher. So usually you say פלוני בן פלוני, ploni ben ploni,
right?
Like מיכאל בן אליהו עד, Michael ben Eliyahu ed,
right? Or you'd say something like that. But this, here's some sort
of variations
of this. You just, you just, you know, so Let's say you
did, you said איש פלוני עד, ish ploni ed, maybe you
didn't say, you know, first name
son of his first
name, but you just said Michael
עד, ed, right? That you know, that might be good. It would
be good. בן איש פלוני עד. ben ish ploni
ed. So or if
you just said the son of, you know, whoever it is, like
בן אליהו, ben Eliyahu, right? You didn't say your first name, you
just
said בן אליהו ben Eliyahu and then you're עד. ed.
That's also good, כשר. kasher. איש פלוני בן איש פלוני, ish ploni
ben ish ploni, but you didn't כתב עד, katav ed, right? You
just said, so, you know, מיכאל בן אליהו, Michael ben Eliyahu, but
you didn't say עד. ed. That's כשר kasher because obviously what else
are you doing there signing it if you weren't witnessing it? So
so that's that's also good. וכך היו נקי הדעת שבירושלים
עושים.
v'kach hayu nikae hadaat
sheb'yerushalayim osim.
And that's what
the I guess it's sort of hard to translate what נקי הדעת,
nikae hadaat, like the scrupulous ones, you know, those of refined, you
know, pure mind, you know, character, whatever. So those kind of people
did that. Why? I don't know what's so special about doing this,
though there
are also those that say that
it goes on the next line, which is כתב חניכתא וחניכתא כשר.
katav chanichata v'chanichata kasher. If you sort of use a nickname, they
say. We're supposed to do all that, remember? You're supposed to write
all the, unless you just use a nickname. That's according to the
פשט, pshat, but it might just also be if you use some
sort of like family name, like let's say you wrote like Waxman
family or something like that, or whatever it is, you know. Or
you'll see, like, you know, the גמרא Gemara will talk more about
that. That's also good. Maybe that's what the נקי הדעת nikae hadaat
did, you know, they wanted to sort of, you know, say there's
nothing special about them, it's the family, you know, I don't know,
maybe. Anyway, but the point is all those are are good. So
now getting on this this first case, the first first case, not
the one that I drew, but the one that's over two columns,
right? And then you sign at the end of it. So וליחוש
דילמא הני תרי גיטי הוו וכתבינהו לזמן דקמא ועידין דבתרא וגזייה לזמן
דבתרא ועידין דקמא. v'lichosh dilma hani trei gitei havu v'katvinhu l'zman d'kama
v'adin d'batra v'gazyei l'zman d'batra v'adin d'kama. So basically the point is
if you have two columns, right? And then you sign at the,
you know, the end, alright, well how do you know it's all
the same גט? get? Like you know, say you cut out one
part and you cut out another part, put them all together, right?
And then it's really two separate גיטין. gittin.
So how do you know it's all going on the same thing,
right? That's basically the question. So אמר רבא כשיהיה רווח מלמטה.
amar Rava kesheyihye
revach milmata.
So it's obvious, right? There's there's a space over here, so it's
obvious that this is continuing it, right? So it's not going to
be, you know what I mean? Because if this if you stopped
in the middle of this picks up where this left off, right,
then it's obviously continuing this. It's the same גט. get. So but
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, "Well, how do you know?"
So ידעתי. yadati. I saw that. I saw I saw you thinking
that. So okay fine, but so what? ודילמא זמן דבתרא מגיז גייז.
u'dilma zman d'batra migaz gayiz. So so what? So I mean, you
know, so okay, so you you know, still cut out some part.
So אמר רב פפא כשיהיה רווח מלמטה הכא נמי כשיהיה רווח מלמעלה.
amar Rav Papa kesheyihye revach milmata hacha nami kesheyihye revach milmala. So
just like we answered this you know part that maybe there's a
space you know below, okay, so here there's also a space above.
Extremely unlikely, right? So this ends here and this takes off right
where that left off, but usually this part
would be full and usually this part would be full. You'd never
do that when
writing something in a column. Like to me that would look more
suspicious, because it looks like someone's waiting to fill in the rest
of that and waiting to fill in the beginning of that. But
it so happens that it's, you know, really, yeah, I hear you,
but but it so happens that if there was no spaces then
I would feel... Well you'll see, you'll see.
The גמרא Gemara you know, perhaps is seeing what what you're saying,
but it's slightly a
slight variance to this. Because they they were there's no way that
they're going to say where that one breaks. You'll see. They they'll
answer that. Okay. ודילמא אימלוכי אימלך וכתב. u'dilma imlochi imlach v'katav. So
maybe what you're saying but also like, you know, different thing is
if somehow like you know, if it's over two columns or and
they're thinking alright you know how I guess it's like all one
thing, you know, it seems like alright
it
was probably written at the same time but it was written over
two columns.
I mean you know, took a break, finished it another day, right?
And then you know then
either it can be a problem of I mean he
finished it, right? So he did want to divorce his
wife, but
it could be a problem of גט ישן,
get yashan, right? It says the first the first column was, you
know, set the date on it, right, you know, whatever it is,
Sunday March 1st, right? Then he finished it in, you know, April
16th, right? Then you know so then
it's a גט ישן get yashan and you know we had all
those problems, what happens if you have like this whole lag between
when it was finished written, you know, then she's considered divorced from
there and you know maybe problems in terms of collecting things. Remember
all that? Or she committed adultery because he divorced her earlier when
it really happened later, right? Whatever, all those all those cases. So
how do you know? Right so now I mean like you know
it ended like mid-sentence right this part ended in הרי את harei
at and then you know this said מוטרת לכל אדם. muteret le-chol
adam. Right? So you're not going to like you know have change
your mind in mid-sentence and then continue it like another day you
know and they know he wanted to divorce her and then thought
better of it and then decided oh no like three months later
well yes divorce her you know what I mean that kind of
like do all that. So the גמרא Gemara says oh maybe maybe
that's exactly what happened ודילמא כולי האי u-dilma kulei hai וחיישינן? ve-chashinan?
Now like come on you know that much you're not going to
be worried about. רש״י אמר Rashi amar דידע ביה מתחתא דמגילתא. de-yada
beih mi-tachtah de-megilta. So basically like you know we when we see
paper we just like you know see our like normal printing you
know paper but like you could tell that it's all it's not
like two separate you know remember our whole question was maybe he
cut out this part and put that here and put that there
right? So his other answer is like no you can sort of
like see it's all like the same paper right each paper has
its own characteristics back then we would actually wrote on them like
you know you had to produce each piece of paper right you
wrote on vellum or whatever it is or קלף klaf or something
you know like you can see that like you know it like
it has you know what I'm saying like if you cut a
piece of wood you know you can sort of see the grain
right? So it's all like one grain. So that's that's the way
they had a special way of treating paper so you could sort
of tell from like you know the one of his point was
like you know the real questions were you know initially how do
you know that like you know it's all one גט get maybe
cut out one part and you know mushed it together with another
and they said oh no because you had spaces so it's obviously
all the same גט get and oh but maybe whatever. So here
he's saying yes it is all one paper but like you know
but his point is that like you know in terms of addressing
the worries about maybe you mixed and matched two different גטין gittin
you can tell it's all the same one. Like glue on no
but like I guess for instance like let's say you like something
between two pieces of paper well look at it this way like
let's say you know you have like aged paper and like brand
new paper then you know and half of it is aged and
the other half is brand new you'd be able to tell that
you know so but so that's assuming that they had two pieces
of paper stuck together like no I'm saying so that's how you
get around it right it's all one piece of paper. No my
point is that each paper like you know had its own characteristics
back then so you know so you can tell it was like
the same piece of paper and that it wasn't like a mixed
and match cut and paste job. So that's that's his answer. ורב
ve-Rav is suggesting that the way it had the the borders would
have a different coloration so that you could see the what would
have the borders would have a different coloration yeah a little bit
darker. So I'm saying like you know each paper had its own
characteristic and now it's fine I mean like just I mean she
can you can see it but the the point is you can
tell from the paper that it's like
not a not a
chop job. Okay so חתם עדים בראש הדף chatam edim be-rosh ha-daf
so that you know the saying they signed at the at the
top of the דף daf or at the side of the דף
daf right then that's not good. איני? eini? Is that really so?
והא רב חתם מן הצד? ve-ha Rav chatam min ha-tzad? ורב ve-Rav
actually did sign from the sides. דהתם בשגגו כלפי הכתב. de-hatam bi-shgago
kelapei ha-ktav. So like I guess what they're saying is oh this
really doesn't erase look at that it's faceless it's like you gotta
really push down on this to erase it. Use the other yeah.
Okay so you know our the way we were thinking about it
is you know הרי את מוטרת harei at muteret and then you
signed over here עד ed right and that's not good. And then
he said oh but רב Rav did it. So the answer is
no he didn't really do it that way he sort of did
it this way so like you know the top of the the
top of the he did it that way so
why that makes it better? Well I kind of had a hard
time understanding that. But anyway his point was בשגגו bi-shgago like the
roof meaning the top of the letters that's the way I understood
it שגגו shigago the roofs of the letters is כלפי הכתב kelapei
ha-ktav facing the you know the text whatever you know the גט.
get. So אלא הא דתניא הקיף ראשו של זה בצד ראשו של
זה ועדים באמצע שניהם פסולין. ela ha de-tanya hikif rosho shel zeh
be-tzad rosho shel zeh ve-edim be-emtza shenehem psulin. So what about that
other case which was which we had before that this first one
was which one was this? This one yeah yeah. So what about
this one right case number one which you said is not good
and we had the roof of this facing the כתב ktav of
that and we said that it's not good and
here רב Rav is saying it is good right get the question?
Like this didn't work right the
roof of this faced like you know. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will
talk about that. Like you know the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* will- the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will- for example, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* will- רב
Rav *Rav* you know with the heads of the letters it
says face the text, meaning it's written actually on the top. No,
I mean it's written like this.
You want to draw? Well just show you. Sure, one second, one
second, one second. Is that what you did and I didn't see?
I couldn't read it. Like that, right? Yeah and the heads face
them. Yeah, that's what I thought. Okay, no no it's fine. It
should be a little larger. Okay so basically what they're saying is,
so what they're saying that רב *Rav* did, רב *Rav* did this,
right? And what the משנה Mishna *Mishna* was thinking was when is
it a problem when he did it the other way around?
The other side? Right, facing outwards is no good, but רב *Rav*
facing inwards it would be good, right? But then you know, that
one it would be facing. Hmm? The- the number one, the two
heads facing each other and the- no no no I'm saying like
in other words forget that for a second. In other words, our
משנה Mishna, *Mishna* said it was bad, right? We thought it meant
this, that's just normally just off to the side, but the question
is רב *Rav* did it off to the side. So now the
answer is רב *Rav* did it like sideways, you know with the
heads of the כתב *ksav* facing this, and therefore when our משנה
Mishna *Mishna* says it's no good, it's the other way around when
it face away, right? How'd you get that from that example? Oh,
oh, oh they're trying to just answer it, you know? I mean
like, you'll see like if it's- if it's signing in the middle
it has to be facing one of them. Yeah, yeah, well no
no we're going to get to that. We're going to get to
that. That's like the next- we're just sort of in interim stage.
That's like the next line literally. So, so but then the question
is you know, but they said okay, what about- what about that
case? And one second. ודאי דהאי מנכר וכלפי הכתב לישתקע *V'dai d'hai
minkar v'cholpei haksav lishtaka* but we're really saying that you know all
you have to do is get the one that's facing the כתב
*ksav*, you know and then and that would be good, then why
is this bad, right? Look which one is facing the כתב *ksav*,
by this it's sort of, you know, which- which has its
roof to the roof of the other one?
So why is it not good? None of them are good, right?
This one should be okay. That's what they're saying. If all you
need to do is have a roof face the- I know it's
a little different here it's like sideways but over here it's like
literally one face the other, but the thinking would be all the
same. התם דדמי ליה כעיבורא *Hatam d'dami lei k'ivura*. So no, so
the- so the answer is is that in our משנה Mishna *Mishna*'s
case what they're- what they're saying is that really it's not like
this what we thought, but rather it's the like this, right? That
meaning when the משנה Mishna: *Mishna* said it's no good, it would
be when the signatures are like vertical. Right. Or yeah, I mean
well sort of also, you know what I mean. Said horizontal, so
to speak. So again, it's always more helpful to look at the
blackboard than me talking about this but whatever. So I'll do the
rest of the גט get. *get* here. So that- that would be
the problem. So then the question is, אי הכי סיפא דקתני ראשו
של זה בצד ראשו של זה והעדים באמצע שניהן כשרים *Ee hachi
seifa d'katni rosho shel ze b'tzad rosho shel ze v'ha'eidim b'emtza shneihan
k'sheirim*. This other case, these other cases which are good,
that ראשו של זה בצד
ראשו של זה *rosho shel ze b'tzad rosho shel ze* which is
a number- case number three. ואי דדמי ליה כעיבורא *V'ee d'dami lei
k'ivura*. If you say that our whole משנה Mishna *Mishna* is talking
about things written on the side, we're assuming that you know we
said for that the- that the same way you signed the- the
signatures were done all the same way, just different cases, right? Like
let's say you put the head of this and the head of
that, or the tail of this and the head of that, all
these cases, they're assuming they're all signed the same way, just like
different case scenarios. But if we're saying the way they signed was
really vertical here, right, case number three on the board, if it's
really that way, not horizontally, then why do we say, ואי דדמי
ליה כעיבורא לא בהדי האי מנכר ולא בהדי האי מנכר *V'ee d'dami
lei k'ivura lo bahadi hai minkar v'lo bahadi hai minkar*. So if
it's this way then which one is it going on, right? You
don't know if it's going on this one or on that one,
right? לא אידין ניכרים עמו *Lo idin nikarim imo*, right? This case.
It helps also look. How do you know, right?
So you know, it's going on either of them.
So the answer is fine, אלא רב בדוכתי הוה חתים
*Ela Rav b'duchti hava chatim*.
So the answer is throw- throw all that out, you know, our
whole thing was oh רב *Rav* managed to do it, right?
How did we- and we tried to like you know go through
a הקפה *hakafa* to make this all work out? Forget about that.
Everything was as we understood it to begin with. No vertical signatures,
everyone's signing horizontally like you normally would. And what about רב? We
can't make it work out anyway. It wasn't your case when רב
was signing things wasn't for a גט. get He just signed like
other court orders, you know, and that's what was okay.
Yeah, it's
some sort
of
a court order that he just like, you know, just approved,
right? What it really...
what it literally means, at least the
way they translate this
here, it's
like a summons. Yeah. רש"י, Rashi, where was
this? Is there a
רש"י Rashi on this? I can't find it
right
now. Anyways, it's a summons. So he was sort of like approving
it, you know, yes I approve that you can summon this guy,
but it wasn't like anything like legally binding in that way. Actually
interesting, like, you know, I think רבי Rabbi Linz maybe wanted to
point out like a רש"י Rashi which had a... like an English
word that we use, like yesterday, he couldn't find it. There's one
today, if you just look, just as a matter of curiosity on
the משנה when it says דף השני, Daf Hasheni, to look at
the first רש"י Rashi on that, the last word, קולומייא, columia, column.
He
says
דף daf doesn't mean a
separate paper, it means column, I think that's the word, column. Anyway,
moving on. So now I already mentioned this as I said the
משנה, but now this is the part the גמרא Gemara talks about.
It's all of three lines... all three words, that that
whole part where גט שכתבו עברית,
get shekatvo Ivrit, you know, different...
written one language, right to left let's say, and then signed
left
to right, all those variations were all fine.
And then כתב סופר ועד, katav sofer ve'ed, the
סופר, sofer, literally
I'm translating it,
סופר sofer wrote
and the
עד ed signed, it's כשר. kasher.
אמר רבי ירמיה חתם סופר ושני עדים.
Amar
Rabi
Yirmiyah hatam sofer ushnei edim. This doesn't mean that the סופר sofer
just wrote it, it means he also signed it.
ואמר רב חסדא מן רב יוסי היא.
Ve'amar Rav Chisda
man Rav Yossi hi.
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda said yeah this is in accordance
with רב יוסי Rav Yossi
that, you know, how is he allowed to sign? Because the סופר
sofer is only allowed to sign if you hear things directly from
the husband. So if the husband... if that's the only way you
can do things then you obviously ask the סופר sofer to sign.
But if you can say that you don't need to hear things
directly from the husband, then we're worried that you asked the סופר
sofer to sign just to make him happy because you know, he's
writing this whole גט get, and you know, so alright let's not
embarrass him by not having him sign, but the husband never asked
for that. And then if he does sign and the proper witness
doesn't sign, it'll be a
whole problem as
I explained earlier.
That's what all that was about. That make sense? Remember that? Yes,
you sure? Okay, so I'll go on.
ההוא כתובתא דחתני, Hahu ktuvta dchatanei, a כתובה, ktubah, I don't know
why they call it כתובת חתנים, ktuvat chatanim, I mean I don't
know what else you have a
כתובה ktubah for, but the...
literally a כתובה ktubah of bridegrooms, of grooms, דאתאי לקמיה
דרבי אבהו דהוה ידעי ליה לטופסא ולחתימת ידא דחד סהדא. de'atai lekamei
deRabi Abbahu dehava yadei lei letufsa ulechitmat yada dechad sahada. So they
knew, they recognized the handwriting, that's what לטופסא letufsa means, handwriting. So
they recognized the סופר, sofer, right? And they also recognized the signature
of one עד. ed. So they say, so forget about like trying
to verify that second one, they figured alright, you know, we already
know enough and if you interpret our משנה to say that if
you recognize the handwriting of the סופר sofer and the signature of
one of the עדים aidim it's כשר, kasher, so let's not even
bother verifying the other one. So we'll say it's good. סבר רבי
אבהו לאכשורה, Savar Rabi Abbahu le’achshurah, so he... he wanted to say
it's fine. אמר ליה רבי אבא לאו חתם סופר ושני עדים תנן.
Amar lei Rabi Abba lav hatam sofer ushnei edim tnan. No, no,
no, you have to have two signatures. The only way you can
say that works is if you recognize... you know, that whole thing,
you can't just go based on the handwriting of one and the
signature of the other, you have to have two signatures, right? And
that was our משנה's case that it allowed two signatures. If one
was a סופר sofer and according to רב יוסי. Rav Yossi. Okay
fine. כתב חניכתו וחניכתה כשר. Katav chanichato vechanichata kasher. So if you
wrote like here, like, you know, like nickname can also sort of
mean like in this case it's going
to be like a
surname. So you wrote like, you know, last name how like... whatever
it is, you know, Goldberg marries Bernstein, right? Or Goldberg divorces Bernstein
in this case. תנו רבנן חניכת אבות בגיטין עד י' דורות. Tanu
Rabanan chanichat avot begitin ad yod dorot. ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר
ג' דורות כשר. VeRabi Shimon ben Elazar omer gimmel dorot kasher. Now
this doesn't necessarily mean a last name, it could mean like, you
know, like בן אליהו, Ben Eliyahu, right? Like you see this all
the time actually in the תורה, Torah, where it says... I'm
trying to
think of like a good example, like when they talked about...
it says in...
and
as a side point very interesting, it says in the ברית בין
הבתרים Brit Bein Habetarim in פרשת לך לך Parshat Lech Lecha ודור
רביעי ישובו
הנה, Vedor revii yashuvu heina, right?
The fourth generation will come back, right? So it means give you
four generations like four kids, grand, whatever, all that, like four generations,
like great whatever, great-grandchild, great-grandparent... kids. So then, so then, no you,
father, grandfather, and great-grandfather. Not great-great, that's four. You include everyone on
there. So and then they said oh because you know they... But
then, so it is four generations. But you look at דברי הימים,
Divrei HaYamim, it's actually ten generations. Like they skipped, the תורה Torah
skipped six whole generations. So the point is though, like sometimes, you
know, if you have like a very famous ancestor, you'll say בן
ben whatever. Like שאול Shaul בן ben קיש, Kish, right? קיש Kish
was this, you know, amazing guy. So like if you say, you
know, or בן דוד, ben David, whatever, right? So you know, you
want to use that, you know? So how long can you like,
you know, capitalize on the luster of that ancestor, right? Can it
be, can it be, so how far can you go? How many
generations can you do this? תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, כתב חניכתבות בגיטין
עד י' דורות ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר ג' דורות. chatav chanichatabot
begitin ad yud dorot v'rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer gimmel dorot. So
ten generations or three generations. So it might ten generations like literally,
like it might be really ten generations. Like sometimes ten is like
this round number, means like a long time, forever, right? But if
they really mean like here up to ten generations, and it might
also be because what I said, like it really in this דברי...
Divrei... they don't say this here, but I remember this, you know,
reading this in the שיעור shiur someplace, that you really, you know,
can go back to ten generations. So how do you know? So
anyway, מכאן ואילך פסול. mikan v'ilech pasul. So after ten or three,
whichever one it is, but after that you can't. So כמאן אזלא
הא דאמר רב חנינא כתב חניכתבות בגיטין עד ג' דורות כמאן? kman
az ha d'amar Rav Chanina chatav chanichatabot begitin ad gimmel dorot kman?
So who does the three-generation thing go by? כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר.
KeRabbi Shimon ben Elazar. אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: מאי קרא?
mai kra? So it goes like that position that now is supported
by a פסוק pasuk רב הונא Rav Huna cites, it just said
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, how
do you know? Fine, you say it goes like רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, but where does he get it from? So it says, מאי
קרא: mai kra: כי תוליד בנים ובני בנים ונושנתם. ki tolid banim
u'vnei vanim v'noshanitem. So that's what we read actually on תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av day, when you have children and grandchildren ונושנתם v'noshanitem and
you'll be there a long time in the land and
then you'll start committing עבודה זרה avodah zarah and you'll be chased
out, right? מהר, maher, you'll be chased out quickly. Actually gonna get
back to that, so that's why I said quickly. כי תוליד בנים
ובני בנים וישבתם על הארץ ונושנתם והשחתם ועשיתם פסל תמונת כל ועשיתם
הרע בעיני יהוה אלהיך להכעיסו העידתי בכם היום את השמים ואת הארץ
כי אבד תאבדון מהר.
ki tolid banim u'vnei vanim v'ishavtem al ha'aretz v'noshanitem v'hishchatem va'asitem pesel
temunat kol va'asitem hara b'einei Hashem
Elohecha l'hachiso haidoti vachem hayom et hashamayim v'et ha'aretz ki avod tavedun
maher. So God says that you'll be chased out quickly. Anyway, but
the point is ונושנתם v'noshanitem means you'll be there a
long time in the land, but what he's saying: בנים ובני בנים,
banim u'vnei vanim, so you, children, grandchildren, ונושנתם, v'noshanitem, then it becomes
too old, right? Up until then it's current, after that it becomes
too old and you can't, that's why they're דרשן darshening this, and
then you can't use it as your identification. So what's interesting is
they didn't explain how the ten generations come from, where the ten
generations come from, and they don't have, no one says anything, so
which is funny. But it's what I, but it might be what
I, at least I don't see anything, how you know, where that
comes from, for ten generations. But it might come from what I
told you. So what'd you say? Where does it talk about it?
The first one was חניכתבות בגיטין עד י' דורות, chanichatabot begitin ad
yud dorot, until ten generations, and then רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר
ג' דורות כשר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer gimmel dorot kosher. He
says three generations. So they cited a proof for the three generations,
they didn't cite any proof for the ten generations. So I'm saying
it might be what I said. So anyway, כמאן אזלא הא דאמר
רב חנינא כתב חניכתבות בגיטין... kman az ha d'amar Rav Chanina chatav
chanichatabot begitin... I said that. Fine. So אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי:
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: נאציי דאגדתא. na'atzei d'aggadata. So nice little
break. אגדתא aggadata is that about this whole idea. לא חבה ארץ
ישראל עד שבאו בה ז' בתי דינים עבודה זרה. Lo chava Eretz
Yisrael ad she'avu ba zayin batei dinim avodah zarah. Interesting. Until seven
literally courts in succession, or of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but they
don't mean courts, what they really mean is like kingdoms, like king,
like dynasties, whatever you want to call it, like kings, right? Somehow
they're called בתי דינים. batei dinim. ואלו הן: V'eilu hein: ירבעם בן
נבט Yerovam ben Nevat one, ואכא בן אחיה v'Acha ben Achaya two,
אחאב בן עמרי Achav ben Omri three, יהוא בן נמשי Yehu ben
Nimshi four, פקח בן רמליהו Pekach ben Remalyahu five, מנחם בן גדי
Menachem ben Gadi six, הושע בן אלה Hoshea ben Elah is seven.
So all those seven were עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah zarah, and
then what happened? שנאמר: Shene'emar: אמללה יולדת השבעה. umlala yoledet hashivah. So
the one who, the יולדת השבעה, yoledet hashivah, like you know, often
times things are inverted in פסוקים, pesukim, the one who bore seven,
they don't mean children in this case, it's being, I mean, whatever
it means, but how it's דרשן darshened over here is not seven
children literally, but the one who had seven, you know, dynasties, whatever
you want to call them, seven you know generations of kings, is
אמללה, umlala, is desolate, meaning there's no one left because they're all
chased from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. נפחה נפשה, Nafcha nafshah, she's like
you know complete misery, באה שמשה בעוד יומם, ba shamshah be'od yomam,
it's like her sun has set even in the middle of the
daytime, meaning like you know there's nothing left, like if your sun
sets that's like the end of you. בושה וחפרה, Bosha v'chafra, she's
you know embarrassed and ashamed. So anyway, so the point is that
after you have like seven royal families you know who are all
עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah zarah, then ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is
אמללה, umlala, you know, it's all desolate because no one's living there
anymore. So אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi מאי קרא mai kra
כי תוליד בנים ובני בנים. ki tolid banim u-vnei banim. So how
do you know you learn from the same thing but how do
you get seven out of that, right? You know, we just said
seven בתי דינים batei dinim and you say oh yeah you learn
it from the כי תוליד בנים ובני בנים. ki tolid banim u-vnei
banim. Didn't we just say it meant three? So I mean
this is not a convincing explanation but תוספות Tosafot says there is
you, right? So you are generation one, then you have בנים. banim.
בנים banim means two, right? So now you get another two. And
then בני בנים. bnei banim. בן בן בן בן. ben ben ben
ben. Get that? So then you get four. Four, two and one
is seven. Seven people. Yeah, okay, but like you know this is
all sort of a little loose. But you
can see what I did over there. So if you expand the
tree each by two, you add them all up you get seven.
So that's where you get it from. אמר ליה רב כהנא לרב
אשי דכתיב ביה בהושע בן אלה ויעש הרע בעיני ה' רק לא
כמלכי ישראל. Amar lei Rav Kahana le-Rav Ashi de-chtiv beih be-Hoshea ben
Elah va-ya'as ha-ra be-einei Hashem rak lo ke-malchei Yisrael. וכתיב עליו עלה
שלמנאסר. U-chtiv alav alah Shalmaneser. So he's saying okay, he wasn't so
great, but he wasn't as bad as everyone before him. So why,
you know, so he wasn't so bad, why was he the last
straw? Meaning like you know God could have waited a little, let
them be completely bad. So why were they then exiled? אמר ליה
אותן פריסדאות שהושיב ירבעם בן נבט שלא יעלו ישראל לרגל בא הושע
וביטלן.
Amar lei otan prosda'ot she-hoshiv Yeravam ben Nevat she-lo
ya'alu Yisrael la-regel ba
Hoshea u-vitlan. You know
as a
matter of fact how is he not so bad? Because back in
the days of ירבעם בן נבט Yeravam ben Nevat he wanted to
establish you know his area as a
center. There's always a
division between the Kingdom of the North and Kingdom of the South.
But you know obviously the part that had the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash had something everybody going for them. People were coming there. But
you know if you
want to have
a new center and make yourself the main thing, so that's what
ירבעם בן נבט Yeravam ben Nevat did. He set all right new,
he actually made these עגלים, agalim, these עגל. egel. He made an
עגל, egel, put it in the north, said this is your new
God. And then he actually had people controlling the area, meaning he
wouldn't let people out of his area to go down to the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So he had you know border control, right?
So this guy, this last of the seven kings, he actually, all
right no more border control, you can go down to the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So okay so if he did all that, then
why, if anything this should be better, right? So why did ה'
Hashem then chase him out of ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? So the
answer is אפילו הכי לא עלו ישראל לרגל. afilu hachi lo alu
Yisrael la-regel. So by now it wasn't the king's forbidding the people
to go, the people didn't want to go anymore. Is this in
פרקי אבות? Pirkei Avot? The what? This whole part? Is this in
פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot about that he was punished... הוא חטא והחטיא
את הרבים. Hu chata ve-hichti et ha-rabbim. ירבעם בן נבט חטא והחטיא
את הרבים. Yeravam ben Nevat chata ve-hichti et ha-rabbim. Yeah, but like
this end part of it? No, it doesn't say. No, it doesn't
say about the people didn't go. It just says חטא והחטיא את
הרבים. chata ve-hichti et ha-rabbim. That's it. אין לו חלק לעולם הבא.
ein lo cheilek le-olam ha-ba. That's the part in פרקי אבות. Pirkei
Avot. Maybe you have some explanation over so אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא
אותן שנים שלא עלו ישראל לרגל ילכו בשבי. Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu
otan shanim she-lo alu Yisrael la-regel yelchu ba-shvi. God said, all right
you don't want to come? All right so now you're not going
to be able to go, right? So now you'll be exiled. So
that's the answer. So yeah, so he wasn't as bad, but the
people were bad, so they merited being exiled. Who's to blame for
them? He was blamed for their not going down. חטא והחטיא. Chata
ve-hichti. Well this is ירבעם בן נבט. Yeravam ben Nevat. But this
last part is already by the seven generations later in the time
of הושע בן אלה Hoshea ben Elah the last king. Right. Right,
but no I'm saying I know what you're saying, that's why I'm
saying all that wasn't in פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avot. But yes he
did, he blamed it and he caused people to do עבודה זרה
avodah zarah with those with the עגל. egel. Yeah that part is
in פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avot. But the whole rest of this is
you know subsequent. So anyway so God said all right now you
don't want to go anymore I'm not going to let you go
so now you'll be exiled. אמר רב חסדא אמר מר עוקבא ואמרי
לה אמר רב חסדא אמר רב ירמיה דרש מרימר. Amar Rav Chisda
amar Mar Ukva ve-amri lah amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Yirmiyah darsh
Mareimar. מאי דכתיב וישקוד ה' על הרעה ויביאה עלינו כי צדיק ה'
אלהינו? mai de-chtiv vayishkod Hashem al ha-ra'ah vayevi'eha aleinu ki
tzaddik Hashem
Elokeinu? God does וישקוד vayishkod
is translate like almost like the שקדיה. shkedia. Like the שקדיה shkedia
blossoms quickly, right? That's why we sing השקדיה פורחת. ha-shkedia porachat. It's
one of the first ones to blossom. So in the same idea
over here, so basically it blossomed, it happened quicker. וישקוד ה' על
הרעה. Vayishkod Hashem al ha-ra'ah. God made it happen quicker ויביאה עלינו
vayevi'eha aleinu and brought it upon us because כי
צדיק ה' אלהינו ki tzaddik Hashem Elokeinu because God is righteous. So
what do you mean? משום דצדיק ה' אלהינו וישקוד ה' על הרעה
ויביאה עלינו? mishum de-tzaddik Hashem Elokeinu vayishkod Hashem al ha-ra'ah vayevi'eha aleinu?
That's a good thing? Because God is righteous He made the evil,
the bad stuff, happen early? How's that good? It says yes, it
actually is. So the idea is just briefly is that the גלות
galut didn't happen all at once, it happened in stages. There was
יכוניה, Yechonyah, as we said you know in מגילת אסתר, Megillat Esther,
עם הגולה אשר הגלתה עם יכוניה מלך יהודה. im ha-golah asher hogleitah
im Yechonyah melech Yehudah. So there's all that, יכוניה מלך יהודה. Yechonyah
melech Yehudah. So there was that part, and then the second part
was שגלתה גלות צדקיה. she-galtah galut Tzidkiyah. That the, so that's the,
you know, that's the second part. So שדקדק הקדוש ברוך הוא מישראל
שהגלה גלות צדקיהו ועדיין גלות יכוניה קיימת. she-dikdek Hakadosh Baruch Hu mi-Yisrael
she-heglah galus Tzidkiyahu ve-adain galus Yechonia kayames. So, meaning like the first
exile happened a little bit before and they were able to already
settle in בבל Bavel and prepare the way for the rest of
the exiles in the second shift. So by the time they got
there, they already had, you know, their needs taken care of, at
least they were focusing more on their spiritual needs, already had בתי
מדרשות, batei midrashos, they already had, you know, the חכמים chachamim over
there, they already had a way of learning תורה, Torah, so they
weren't like completely rudderless and adrift. So, as it says, דכתיב ביה
בגלות יכוניה החרש והמסגר אלף. de-chsiv bei be-galus Yechonia hacharash ve-hamasgeir elef.
החרש והמסגר Hacharash ve-hamasgeir were a thousand people. Literally, it means like
these different, you know, חרש charash is like some sort of, like,
crafts people, craftsmen, and מסגר masgeir is as in לסגור, lisgor, like
a gatekeeper. So there are a thousand of those. So you know,
literally it means like, you know, people doing, you know, sort of
manual labor of some sort, but they're taking this to mean more
homiletically, חרש שבשעה שפותחין נעשו הכל כחרשין. charash she-be-sha'ah she-poschin na'asu hakol
ke-chereshin. They're the חכמים. chachamim. Why are they called חרש? charash? Because
like, you know, when they, when they, you know, spoke everyone's like
deaf, meaning like you know, they only hear for them I guess,
deaf to other things, deaf to other outside influence, or that they
couldn't speak, חרש cheresh also means like, you know, שומע ואינו מדבר,
shomeia ve-eino medaber, like, you know, when they spoke no one else
would speak because like, you know, they're so authoritative no one would
second-guess them. That's one. And then מסגר כיון שסוגרין, masgeir keivan she-sogrin,
once they, you know, they closed, that's it, we're done, you know,
we decided, שוב אין פותחין. shuv ein poschin. So, no one, you
know, the case won't be reopened, right? Once you decided that this
is the way it's going to be, that's the way it's going
to be. So, וכמה אלף, ve-kamah elef, and there were a thousand.
And there were a thousand of those. So already there were a
thousand of these great sages over there by the time from the
first exile, so by the time the second exile got there, everything
was all set up for them. So that's one way God is
righteous. So the other the other way he's righteous, עולא אמר שהקדים
שתי שנים לונושנתם. Ulla amar she-hikdim shtei shanim le-ve-noshantem. So if you
do the גימטריא gematria of ונושנתם, ve-noshantem, you get 852, but rather
God exiled them after 850 years. That was וישקוד השם על הרעה,
vayishkod Hashem al hara'ah, God hastened it. So means not like God
made it like the next day, right? He waited 850, 50 years.
But why was why was that good? He sort of blocks off
the end of it, but the end of it was after that,
העדותי בכם היום כי אבוד תאבדון, ha'idosi bachem hayom ki avod toveidun,
you'll be totally, you know, you'll be totally annihilated. So the point
being that if God had waited the full time frame, then there'd
be nothing left of the Jewish people. So why is it a
צדקה tzedakah that God did? So God hastened the רעה ra'ah by
two years in order they wouldn't destroy the entire Jewish people. That's
why השם Hashem is called a צדיק. tzaddik. So yes, it was
a
little earlier, but the tradeoff was the Jewish people were still around.
Yeah, it's just kind of related to the story about coming out
of Egypt, you know, where they said had he left them too
late there'd be no
hope for them, they would
never be able to get out. It's like the reverse. He got
them, he got them out or both, he got them they made
it similar, but got them out in time. Right. Right. Okay, moving
on, אמר רב אחא בר
יעקב שמע מינה מהר
דמרי עלמא תמני מאה וחמישים תותיהו.
Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov shema mina
maher
de-marei alma tamnei mei'ah va-chamishin tuseihu. So you know, because it says
אבוד תאבדון מהר, avod toveidun maher, so מהרה, meheirah, I'm sorry, אמר
רב אחא בר יעקב שמע מינה מהרה. Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
shema mina meheirah. We see the אבוד תאבדון מהר, avod toveidun maher,
so מהרה. meheirah. When God is being quick
about something, it means
850 years. But you know, like we say אלף שנים בעיניך כיום
אתמול, elef shanim be-einecha ke-yom esmol, right? Like a thousand years for
God is like one day. So 850 years, not even part of
a day. So you know, the point is, you know, to show
how compassionate God is, that although God said it would be quick,
you know, it wasn't so quick,
you know,
it was
quite a long time. So you know,
things are on a
relative time frame I guess. So okay, now this this next topic
is also maybe he wanted to be compassionate in case they did
תשובה. teshuvah. Yeah, right. Fair enough. So I don't mean to say
that God is like slow because he's like dawdling, but you know,
the point is that like, you know, he's giving
us a chance, you know. So right.
And he gave us them 850 years to you know make it
right.
So okay, so totally different
topic
and a very important
topic, about, oh also I just wanted to touch on the ten
generations, you know you have that with Abraham, you know, is it
Abraham and Noah in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avos, ten generations, and then
God did it. Right, yeah.
And there was no one left after after after Noah. So maybe
it's kind of similar
stuff here with the ten generations. Oh that's interesting. Yeah, maybe. That's
a good point. גט מעושה. Get me'useh. So a forced,
coerced גט,
get,
right? This is a
big topic, right? Not that long ago there were these people indicted,
it was in New Jersey I think. Or do you remember any
of you read this? Like that these rabbis, you know, sort of
sent, you know, some ruffians to
coerce a... there was
a bunch of these that happened and then you know they
finally got prosecuted and you know I don't know what happened to
them. I think they got... Anyway, so that's the general topic, but
you'll see though that it might not be as like oh my
God, wow, it's really, you know, but
it might be a
little more circumscribed. And
I'm
going to...
it's a very short משנה: גט מעושה בישראל כשר
ובעובדי כוכבים פסול. Get me'useh b'Yisrael kasher uv'ovdei chochavim pasul. So let
me get rid of this. So גט מעושה... Get me'useh... so if
it's... so let's do this. I want to draw a little grid.
So it depends... well actually, you know what, I'll wait till
the גמרא. The
גמרא talks about it. So if it's done by
a Jewish court, that's fine. If it's done
by a non-Jewish court, that's no good. ובעובדי כוכבים פסול. Uv'ovdei chochavim
pasul. עובדי כוכבים חובטים אותו ואומרים לו עשה מה שישראל אומרים לך
כשר. Ovdei chochavim chovtin oto v'omrim lo aseh mah she'Yisrael omrim lecha
kasher. So if the non-Jewish court sounds like they're doing it on
their own volition—why they would do that I don't know—but that'd be
bad. But if they said, "Oh no, you know, do what the
Jewish court is asking you to do," then that'd be okay, right?
So it's only if it's completely under a non-Jewish court that it'd
be a problem. We're going to talk about this in the גמרא.
Well, it sounds like... it sounds like if, you know... right, if
they're enforcement officers based on what the Jewish court is doing and
they're saying that, then that'd be fine. But if they're not saying
any of this and they're doing it
on their own, it'd be a problem. It then becomes enforceable
in a
non-Jewish court if
you're writing
a
contract that will bring in the secular courts. Okay, that sounds pretty
reasonable. Right, and רש״י Rashi only has one word on the משנה
of what מעושה me'useh means: בחזקה. bechezakah. So what I... you know,
what I will tell you though is, like, you know, we obviously—and
maybe we can to an extent—use this as a general principle, like
of the recalcitrant husband, right?
Like,
which
is
what...
a big, big topic right now. But not to... well, the גמרא's
going to talk about it.
So let's get right into it and then I'll explain if that
can completely be applied. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל גט המעושה בישראל
כדין כשר שלא כדין פסול ופוסל.
Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel: Get hame'useh b'Yisrael
k'din
kasher, shelo k'din pasul u'posel. So now we have like two grids.
There's ישראל. Yisrael.
It's not writing too well. Try this again. ישראל. Yisrael.
Then you're going to have, I guess, two grids: דין din and
then לא כדין. lo k'din. לא כדין. Lo k'din. So these are
our two, you know, our two variations, right? So what he says
that if it's גט המעושה בישראל כדין כשר, get hame'useh b'Yisrael k'din
kasher, right? So if it's ישראל Yisrael and דין, din, then that's
good. They're allowed to do it. שלא כדין פסול ופוסל. Shelo k'din
pasul u'posel. What does that mean? פסול Pasul means it doesn't work,
but פוסל posel means it sort of works enough that she can't
marry another כהן. Kohen. That's what פוסל posel means. Like, you... she's
now... she's not... so it's פסול; pasul; she's not divorced from her
husband, but she's divorced enough that she can't marry a כהן, Kohen,
so to speak. That's the only effect it has. It's considered, you
know, that's it. That's what פוסל posel means. So she's still married,
but you don't... she can't marry a כהן Kohen then. Let's say
he dies, right? She's not considered an אלמנה; almanah; she's considered... Wait,
this is how we've been using פסול pasul this whole time? No,
פוסל. posel. פוסל. Posel. פסול Pasul means that... פסול pasul means she's
still married, but like פוסל posel means now she
can't
marry a כהן. Kohen. Let's say... obviously if you divorce her, you
can't marry her anyway if you divorce her again because then she's
really fully divorced. No matter what, but פוסל posel means let's say
he dies, right? Or whatever other things you have, you know, תרומה,
terumah, whatever. I don't know. But that's what פוסל posel means. ובעובדי
כוכבים כדין פסול ופוסל. Uv'ovdei chochavim k'din pasul u'posel. So that'd be
sort of like here, right? That'd be the same thing: פסול ופוסל.
pasul u'posel. Just... it's like a step
down, right? שלא כדין פירכא אין בו. Shelo k'din pircha ein bo.
Nothing, right? All right, so it's the total opposite, right? So of
what we said before. If it's שלא כדין shelo k'din and
done by a
non-Jewish court, it means absolutely nothing, right?
They're totally married. So basically, what is כדין, k'din, right? I said
I sort of skipped over that, right?
כדין. K'din. What
does
a ישראל Yisrael coercing something כדין k'din mean, right? So רש״י Rashi
says כדין: k'din: כגון הנך דאמרינן בהו יוציא ויתן כתובה או שהיתה
אסורה לו.
kegon hanach d'amrinan behu yotzi v'yiten
kesubah o she'haysah asurah lo. So when they're doing it, I'll say,
for cause. It doesn't mean that the Jewish court is saying, "Okay,
listen..." And you've been waiting,
you know, normal case,
like it's been ten years, you haven't, you know, you said you
were going to give your wife
a
גט, get, you haven't done it. It's not
that kind
of a case. It's not that the, you know, they want to
get divorced and the husband's just holding out. It means in those
cases, but the, in those cases where the marriage isn't supposed to
continue. Like let's say
a כהן Cohen marries a
whatever it is, you
know,
גרושה, grusha, or something like that. Whatever all the cases we had
before. You know, I don't know about כהן Cohen and גרושה, grusha,
but the whatever cases we said before, that שהייתה אסורה לו, she-hayetah
asurah lo, those, you know, where the marriage wasn't allowed to happen
to begin with. Might
be, might be a כהן Cohen and גרושה, grusha, I don't know.
But like whatever it, you know, all those פסולים, psulim, you know,
that, that weren't, I don't know the exact scope of the case,
but it isn't the normal case of, you
know, husband and
a
wife, they married, or you know, everything was, you know, fine until
they decided to get divorced and the husband's holding out. No, it's
a case, it's a case
of the husband and wife shouldn't have been married to begin with.
And then the פסק psak was יוציא ויתן כתובה, yotzi v'yiten ktubah,
and now the בית דין Beis Din is enforcing that you do
so. That's the case we're talking about. Then if the
בית דין Beis Din enforced a
גט, get which was supposed to have been given anyway, but the
husband was holding out, right? Because if he gave it right away,
what's the
problem? So in a case where he should have been
giving the גט and he didn't, then the Jewish court steps in,
then it's okay. And then you have all these other, you know,
cases. But you can't necessarily abstract, I don't know, whether we do
or don't, you know, can't necessarily
abstract to like a modern analogue of, you know, spousal refusal and
the recalcitrant husband.
All right. And that's how it would apply to like a situation
where...